Rost?
Rost!
ROST!
Where is he?
Two days before the proving and he goes off without me?
He wouldn't do that.
He said we'd go hunting this morning.
Why isn't he here?
Where has he gone to?
What's he doing up there?
He's just standing there.
What's going on with him?
Aloy.
You're here.
When you said we were gonna go hunting
I didn't realise you meant I'd have to track you down.
We must speak.
I've been thinking about your training Aloy.
You've learned to hunt, learned to survive.
But I fear there's a lesson I failed to teach you.
Would you learn it now?
Of course, I'll always learn what you have to teach.
There's been some trouble recently.
It affords an opportunity to learn this lesson
but it will be dangerous.
You must come prepared
or you will die.
Descend into the Embrace and hunt
until you've gathered the parts for fire arrows.
Fire arrows?
What kind of trouble are we talking about?
Once you have the parts, you will meet me there
at the gate beyond the village of Mother's Heart.
The north gate at the edge of the Embrace?
Yes.
Now be on your way.
Is something else bothering you?
No. I'm fine.
Are you worrying about what happens
after the Proving?
What happens is clear.
You will be accepted as one of the tribe
and I will still be an outcast to be shunned.
Rost, even if the tribe accepts me I won't…
There is much to do Aloy.
We will discuss this later.
[sighs] Okay.
Uhh
Odd Grata might be out of food by now.
You could hunt a week's worth of meat for her
if you find the time.
Wouldn't mind if she'd say thanks just once.
Grata follows the law.
Her silence towards us is honourable, not an insult.
I'll go gather the parts, but i'm also gonna pay Karst a visit.
Aloy…
That man breaks the law every time he speaks to you.
And I'm glad he does.
I want to buy a Tripcaster and no other trader will sell to outcasts.
Stock it with ammunition then.
You'll find use for that weapon tonight.
That sounds ominous.
All right. See you at the north gate.
Something's really bothering him.
If he thinks I'm going to abandon him, he's wrong.
The Embrace.
My whole life I've never gone beyond this valley.
That'll change after the Proving.
Two days.
Two days until I get answers.
Two days and I'll know who she was.
And why I was cast out at birth.
As if there could be an excuse for that.
All right.
Time to gather the parts for some fire arrows.
I should find a herd.
All-Mother.
When my name was called to the mountain
you did not speak it back.
You kept it close to your heart.
I know even when my belly and hands are empty
that you hold me in your embrace.
Hello Grata.
All-Mother, since I was cast out
have I not been constant as the river flows?
Have I not kept the vows as the stones do?
Show me your grace All-Mother
and provide for me once more.
Don't worry Grata, I'll hunt your rabbits.
All-Mother!
I hear your voice on the wind.
I would count your blessings on my prayer beads,
but I lost them atop the eastern overlook.
My old bones are too worn to return.
So it's rabbits and your trinket you need this time.
Okay, I'll find you at your camp.
Calm, calm.
Snow chill. Itches.
Okay, Grata said her prayer beads were at the eastern overlook.
It's not far from here.
The Brave Trail up the rocks is close by.
Grata may be devout but it takes strong arms to reach the overlook the fast way.
Explosions and shouts from outside the Embrace.
I wonder what's going on?
This looks promising.
Aha! Grata's prayer beads.
I see why she comes up here to pray.
It looks out to Mother's Gate.
You know, I wonder what bothers me more.
That she ignores me?
Or that with all her talking to All-Mother she's never lonely.
Tasty.
More than equipped to take you on!
Here we go again…
Pass the test.
Never know when I might need these.
Keep that for later.
That'll keep my stomach quiet.
Time to see Karst and get a Tripcaster.
No-one else around, looks safe to meet.
My guess is he'll be waiting for me.
There he is, looks nervous.
Well, well, well.
An outcast on my doorstep.
All-Mother protect me.
Surprised you saw me the way you keep looking every other direction
to make sure no one's watching.
Careful there you'll sprain your neck.
It's always a pain in the neck when you show up girl,
one way or another.
Is there a reason why you're acting so cranky today?
Once you run the Proving and get made a brave
you'll deal with traders in Mother's Heart.
Maybe I don't like losing customers.
Traders who don't break the law and deal with outcasts you mean?
That's right. Our days of crime will be behind us. So long as you keep quiet.
Are you worried I'm going to tell someone that you trade with outcasts?
I don't think you're the kind who talks…
…but you never know.
You can stop worrying.
Your secret's safe with me.
Yeah, that's what I figured.
But I don't mind hearing it.
The only person I've ever told about our trades is Rost.
Yeah, well not like he can turn me in
even if he wanted to.
Law and duty sort of a man that Rost.
I don't know how you stand it.
You really don't know why he was cast out?
I've told you, no.
I don't think anyone knows what he did,
but it must have been serious because
his term is for life.
Why do you take the risk trading with outcasts?
Every time, you ask.
If a big meaningful talk is what you're after,
move along.
It's because you used to be one, isn't it?
Yeah.
Got caught poking around one of the metal Ruins out beyond the Embrace.
Matriarchs said I was tainted and gave me five years.
What did you see in the ruins?
Nothing I could make sense of.
After my shunning I tried living back in Mother's Heart,
but everyone I knew had moved on
and there were so many people everywhere I turned.
I like it better out here.
Last time I visited you had a Tripcaster available for trade.
Still got it?
I do.
But you need to bring me a Scrapper Lens.
What can I say? Special weapons don't come cheap.
Oh, I can pay.
Took down a Scrapper not long ago.
Stripped out the lens in perfect condition.
I'll be the judge of that. Show me.
Now that you've got yourself a Tripcaster,
practice how to use it someplace else, all right?
My life's exciting enough without a bunch
of shock wire booby traps to trip over.
Really? Could have fooled me.
Will you be around later?
In case I want to make another trade?
I'll be here.
Same as usual bring me the parts you harvest
from any machines you hunt.
The better the parts, the more shards I'll pay.
I guess that concludes our business.
All right, good luck in the Proving.
Blessing of All-Mother and all that.
It's heavy, world's going white.
Fresh as it comes.
No turning back.
There's Grata, all alone with All-Mother.
The only way she knows.
Good news Grata!
Once again All-Mother has brought you rabbits.
I found your prayer beads, too.
Just try not to lose them again.
All-Mother, each morning I find
your tears of joy speckling the leaves.
Joy at the beauty of all you have made.
See how I cry now with you in gratitude.
So you'll cry for her but you won't speak to me.
Fine. Guess that makes you the better outcast.
Grata…
I may not be around much for a while.
I'm gonna run in the Proving and…
I'm not sure what's gonna happen after that.
All-Mother I thank you for the kindnesses you share.
When the Proving comes in your great wisdom,
may you give favour to a brave of generous heart.
I… think I get what you're saying.
Goodbye Grata for now.
I've got what I need.
Time to meet Rost at the north gate.
[offscreen]
Brom! It's your sister Olara!
Saving these for the trail.
Good … meat.
Aloy, you're here.
You have the fire arrows?
I do.
Those explosions and shouts beyond the embrace…
…is that the trouble you were talking about?
You will know soon enough.
Until then we wait for dark.
What can we do from in here?
The lesson will be taught in due time Aloy.
Until then we wait.
I got Odd Grata her rabbits.
For which she thanked All-Mother, of course.
It was All-Mother working through you
to bring her the rabbits.
You always say that but I was there and I hunted alone.
And you always say that and so make yourself alone.
I saw Karst and got that Tripcaster I was talking about.
I hate to think what that outlaw trader
charged for a weapon of that make.
It wasn't cheap, but the 'caster is worth it.
Perhaps.
You'll know it's worth soon enough.
Is something else bothering you?
No. I'm fine.
Are you worrying about
what happens after the Proving?
What happens is clear.
You will be accepted as one of the tribe
and I will still be an outcast.
To be shunned.
Rost, even if the tribe accepts me I…
There is much to do Aloy.
We will discuss this later.
Still a while ago before dark.
I guess I'll get some rest.
Good idea.
There'll be no time for sleep tonight.
[whistles]
[returned whistle from outside]
Opening a gate for an outcast?
Some who are shunned reaped honour before disgrace.
So much for tribal law.
I spoke to no one and now we must both keep silent.
For we are outside of the Embrace.
These are the true wilds Aloy.
With threats unlike any you have ever faced.
T hat carcass!
What sort of beast was that?
The tribe calls it a Sawtooth and it's something new.
Something angry.
Since they first started appearing 10 years ago,
they have killed many braves.
Yeah.
[Rost]
Follow the path it's not far.
That cabin what happened to it?
[Rost]
A machine, that's what.
What sort of machine does that?
[Rost]
The sort of machine you're hunting now.
Oh. I see.
A Watcher carcass. I'll harvest the parts.
[Rost]
Watch your surroundings.
It won't be much farther now.
Why are we the only ones out here tonight?
Why can't the tribe's braves hunt this machine?
[Rost]
They did. The kills we've passed are theirs.
Tomorrow they will hunt again.
They won't need to.
This machine will be my kill.
[Rost]
Or your death if you're not careful.
An entire lodge wrecked.
By Sawtooths?
How many were there?
I didn't bring you here to answer questions Aloy.
I brought you here to deal with that.
It's huge!
How do you defeat it?
That will be for you to decide.
This hunt is yours to make Aloy. Yours alone.
No matter what happens I will not intervene.
You understand?
You are on your own.
I should stay out of sight.
I can use the tall grass to approach.
Okay, let's see. Where can I place my traps?
And now it's on!
I should scan it.
Out of ammo.
I should switch weapons.
Hello!
Why did I bring you here?
Not to answer questions.
Aloy.
Survival requires perfection.
It was a test to hone my skills
against a dangerous new machine.
No. Follow.
These are Nora hunting lands.
They must be protected.
If you hadn't destroyed the sawtooth,
how many braves might it
have killed or injured tomorrow?
The lesson lives within the question Aloy.
For years you've trained to win the Proving
but only for yourself.
As a brave it will be your duty to fight for your tribe.
My tribe?
You said I wouldn't need them.
But I never said the tribe wouldn't need you.
The strength to stand alone Aloy,
is the strength to make a stand.
To serve a purpose greater than yourself.
That is the lesson you must learn.
And remember it after the Proving…
…and after I'm gone.
We're finished here.
Follow.